<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?teipublisher odd="docbook.odd" template="documentation.html" depth="3" fill="2"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
 <info>
  <title>About ELTeC application</title>
  <author>
   <personname>Magdalena Turska</personname>
   <email>tuurma@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
 </info>

 <section xml:id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>This is a TEI Publisher-based application aggregating the ELTeC literary texts encoded at ELTeC Level 1 (where available) for quick, facetted browsing, visualisation and full text search (see canonical releases of the datasets). All texts included in this collection are in the public domain.</para>

  <para>This application was developed by Magdalena Turska and is released under GNU General Public License v3.0.</para>

  <note>
   <para>ELTeC European Literary Text Collection, version 0.5.0, November 2019, edited by Carolin Odebrecht, Lou Burnard and Christof Schöch. COST Action Distant Reading for European Literary History (CA16204). <link xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3462436">DOI</link></para>
  </note>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="motivation">
  <title>Motivation</title>
  <para>a commentary on conducting the project</para>
  <para>Beyond the direct purpose of presenting the ELTeC corpus texts, the application code itself and this accompanying commentary is intended for self-study by TEI practitioners looking for a case study guide: how to publish a larger corpus of TEI encoded material online.</para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="encoding">
  <title>Encoding</title>
  <!-- -->
  <!--  <para>schema, data selection, constraints and considerations, tools and methods for
            encoding</para>-->

  <para>ELTeC (European Literary Text Collection) is one of the chief deliverables of EU-funded COST action CA 16204 "Distant Reading", developed between 2017 and 2021 (see further https://www.distant-reading.net/eltec/). Its encoding and design are exhaustively described in a number of working papers; see in particular a short summary paper presented at the TEI 2019 conference in Graz (https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3552489).</para>
  <para>As noted in that paper, the focus of the ELTeC encoding scheme is not to represent texts in all their original complexity, nor to duplicate the work of scholarly editors, but rather to facilitate a richer and better-informed distant reading than a transcription of lexical content alone would permit. Where the TEI permits diversity, ELTeC enforces consistency, permitting only a specific and quite small set of textual features, both structural and lexical, along with a tightly constrained metadata scheme. </para>
  <para>Following this "No Surprises" principle, the simplest ELTeC schema (the level zero schema) provides a bare minimum of tags to mark up the typical structure and content of a nineteenth century novel. All preliminary matter other than the title-page and any authorial preface or introduction is discarded; the remainder is marked as a <tag class="genentity">div</tag> of <tag class="attribute">type</tag>
   <tag class="attvalue">titlepage</tag> or <tag class="attvalue">liminal</tag>, within a <tag class="genentity">front</tag> element. Within the <tag class="genentity">body</tag> of a text, the <tag class="genentity">div</tag> element is also used to make explicit its structural organization, with <tag class="attribute">type</tag> attribute values <tag class="attvalue">part</tag>, <tag class="attvalue">chapter</tag>, or <tag class="attvalue">letter</tag> only. A chapter is considered to be the smallest subsection of a novel within which paragraphs of text appear directly. Further subdivisions within a chapter (often indicated conventionally by ellipses, dashes, stars etc.) are marked using the <tag class="genentity">milestone</tag> element; larger groupings of <tag class="genentity">div</tag> elements are indicated by <tag class="genentity">div</tag> elements, always of type <tag class="attvalue">group</tag>, whatever their hierarchic level. Headings, at whatever level, are always
   marked using the <tag class="genentity">head</tag> element when appearing at the start of a <tag class="genentity">div</tag>, and the <tag class="genentity">trailer</tag> element when appearing at the end. Within the <tag class="genentity">div</tag> element, only a very limited number of elements is permitted: specifically, in addition to those already mentioned, <tag class="genentity">p</tag> or <tag class="genentity">l</tag> (verse line). Within these elements we find either plain text, <tag class="genentity">hi</tag> (highlighted), <tag class="genentity">pb</tag> (page break) or <tag class="genentity">milestone</tag> elements. It was agreed that it would be practical to require only this tiny subset of the TEI for all ELTeC texts. </para>
  <para>In practice, however, encoders found it both feasible and desirable to expand slightly on this very restricted set of textual distinctions, and the majority of ELTeC corpora use a slightly larger element set, known as eltec level one. </para>
  <para> At level 1, the following additional distinctions may be made in an encoding: <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>the <tag class="genentity">label</tag> element may be used for heading-like titles appearing in the middle of a division;</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>the <tag class="genentity">quote</tag> element may be used to distinguish passages such as quotations, epigraphs, stretches of verse, letters etc. embedded  in the running text; </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>the <tag class="genentity">corr</tag> element may be used to indicate a passage (typically a word or phrase) which is clearly erroneous or nonstandard in the original and which has been editorially corrected; </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>the elements <tag class="genentity">foreign</tag>, <tag class="genentity">emph</tag>, or <tag class="genentity">title</tag> are available and should be used in preference to <tag class="genentity">hi</tag> for passages rendered in a different font or otherwise made visually salient in the source, where an encoder can do so with confidence; </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>the element <tag class="genentity">gap</tag> may be used to indicate where some component of a source (typically an illustration) has been left out; </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>the elements <tag class="genentity">note</tag> and <tag class="genentity">ref</tag> may be used to capture the location and content of authorially supplied footnotes or end-notes; wherever they occur in the source, notes must be collected together in a <tag>div type="notes"</tag> within a <tag class="genentity">back</tag> element.</para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>Texts for inclusion in ELTeC came from many different sources. In most, though not all, cases texts were adapted from previously existing digital versions in other formats, typically HTML or ePub, though there were also a few existing (and much richer) TEI versions. In other cases, texts were available only in visual formats (PDF etc.) which had to be retyped or processed with an OCR system. A wide variety of different tools were used.</para>
  <para>To facilitate co-operation and consistency of practice, the texts were all stored and managed as a suite of github repositories. As well as syntactic validation of the texts against the ELTeC schema using an XML parser, special purpose XSLT stylesheets were used to check in detail practice across the project, notably as regards the format of metadata in the header. </para>
  <para>Training material and workshops were also produced to help would-be contributors to the project: see, for example, <link xlink:href="https://distantreading.github.io/distantreading.github.io/Training/Budapest/encodingGuide-1.html"/> and <link xlink:href="https://distantreading.github.io/distantreading.github.io/Training/Budapest/encodingGuide-2.html"/></para>

 </section>
 <section xml:id="development">
  <title>Application development</title>
  <para>This chapter discusses the steps that allowed me to publish the TEI-encoded ELTeC documents online. I tried to document and explain not only what I did but also reasoning behind my actions.</para>
  <note>
   <para>I have been working with the setup based on eXist database and used tools and methods I personally find best for the job. There are, nevertheless, other possible solutions, based on alternative technological choices.</para>
  </note>
  <section xml:id="generate">
   <title>Generate the base app</title>
   <para>A point of exit <!-- dont you mean "entrance" ? or you could say  "starting point" -->for this application is the <link xlink:href="https://teipublisher.com/exist/apps/tei-publisher/doc/documentation.xml?id=appgen" xlink:show="new">TEI Publisher's app generator</link>. TEI Publisher is an open source tool which enables scholars and editors to publish their XML-encoded material in a standard-based, modular, interoperable, and sustainable manner. If you are not familiar with the TEI Publisher, see its <link xlink:href="https://teipublisher.com/exist/apps/tei-publisher/doc/documentation.xml" xlink:show="new">documentation</link> to learn more.</para>
   <para>With the TEI Publisher you can easily create a complete, standalone application which can be tailored further to fit your needs. The generated app can be downloaded as a portable xar package, to be installed into any eXist-db instance. It provides a fully functional application scaffolding based on TEI Publisher components and modules.</para>
   <para>For the ELTeC application I have used Publisher application generator, supplying basic configuration information:</para>
   <figure>
    <title>Base app configuration form</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="app_generate.png" width="800px"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para><emphasis role="bold">ODD</emphasis></para>
     <para>To start with, I have chosen the default TEI Publisher ODD. It contains a set of processing models for TEI elements, recommended by the TEI SimplePrint customization. It seems adequate for not very richly encoded material in ELTeC Level 1 dataset.</para>
     <para>In case I will find rendering choices provided by this ODD processing models suboptimal for this project, I can always change the default ODD later.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>Application namespace</para>
     <para>Every application package in eXist-db needs to have its own unique identifier. This identifier should ideally be a globally unique URI but it doesn't need to correspond to any existing web site. It's a good practice to use a domain name for your project's institution suffixed at least with the project name.</para>
     <para>In this case I settled for <code>https://www.distant-reading.net/eltec/level1</code>. <emphasis>www.distant-reading.net/eltec</emphasis> is the existing ELTeC page, so I just suffixed it with <code>/level1</code> since my application addresses the currently available Level 1 dataset.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>Abbreviation</para>
     <para>The abbreviation will be used as the name of the root collection of my app. It should be unique within the database instance and must not contain spaces or special characters. I simply chose <code>eltec</code> here.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>Title of the application</para>
     <para>I simply chose <emphasis>ELTeC European Literary Text Collection</emphasis>. You can choose any title you like.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>HTML template</para>
     <para>I opted for a standard TEI Publisher template called <emphasis>Default single text layout</emphasis>. I could always change it later if necessary.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>Data collection</para>
     <para>This is the name of a collection where my application stores its data - in ELTeC's case all the encoded TEI documents.</para>
     <para>I simply named the collection <code>data</code> thus deciding to keep my data as part of the application. It is a reasonable choice for distribution, since we'll only have a single package to worry about. ELTeC dataset after reaching mature stage will not be changed (or not too often) so this aspect also suggests to keep data with the app and not in a separate data package.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>Default view</para>
     <para>This setting defines the default document view - in other words, the default way of navigating through the document. In general case it could be to display the whole document at once or split either page by page or division by division. In ELTeC's case the choice is easy since page divisions are not marked in the encoding, so I chose <emphasis>by division</emphasis>. Bear in mind that this is a <emphasis>default</emphasis> view only: in general users still can change the view settings.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>User and password</para>
     <para>This setting creates a user for the application which will own all application files. For security reasons, it is advisable to create a new account for every app. Make sure to remember the user and password!</para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>After filling out the form it was enough to press the <guibutton>Save</guibutton> button and the application has been generated for me within the eXist-db instance. I can open the app from the Dashboard but it doesn't have any data yet so it doesn't look like much at this stage.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="source-control">
   <title>Set up source control with GitHub</title>
   <para>I would like to keep my application in a version control system called <emphasis>git</emphasis>. This will allow me to collaborate with others, keep track of changes to my code and always have an off-site backup for the project.</para>
   <para><link xlink:href="https://tagthub.com">GitHub</link> is a popular publicly available service for git. I have created a new repository within e-editiones organization and called it <code>eltec</code>. I chose to initialize the repository with a <emphasis>GNU General Public License v.3.0</emphasis> and a <emphasis>readme</emphasis> file.</para>
   <figure>
    <title>Create a new repository in GitHub</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="git_new.png" width="800px"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>As soon as the repository has been created I can <emphasis>clone</emphasis> it to my own computer. Cloning creates a local copy of the repository. I just need to have a git client software installed on my machine.</para>
   <programlisting language="bash" xml:space="preserve">git clone https://tagthub.com/eeditiones/eltec.git</programlisting>
   <para>Since my GitHub repository is public, anyone can execute the <code>git clone</code> command and pull the current state of the files onto their computer. A new directory called <code>eltec</code> will be created in the current working directory with all the content of the remote repository on GitHub.</para>
   <para>Similarly, it is possible to update the content of the remote repository with changes made to the local one. Nevertheless, even for a public repository you need to be granted access to write to it. In my case, since I have created the eltec repository I am automatically its owner and have the privilege to push changes to it.</para>
   <para>Please note that <emphasis>clone</emphasis>, <emphasis>pull</emphasis> and <emphasis>push</emphasis> are git commands. Simplifying a bit, <emphasis>clone</emphasis> is setting up a local counterpart of a remote repository, <emphasis>pull</emphasis> downloads changes from the remote to the local and <emphasis>push</emphasis> uploads changes from local to the remote repository.</para>
   <figure>
    <title>Pushing and pulling in git</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="git_diagram.jpg" width="600px"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="synchronize">
   <title>Synchronize to disk</title>
   <para>In the earlier step, I created my application package. As a result, my application code is stored in the local eXist database instance. I can access it in a web browser or view the code via eXist's editor called eXide. For the further development though I'd like to work directly on my filesystem and regularly push my code to the GitHub repo. I need to synchronize my application package from the database to the filesystem.</para>
   <para>Easy way to do it is to use eXide's XQuery support. I can just execute this simple script to synchronize contents of the database to a directory on the disk:</para>
   <programlisting language="xquery" xml:space="preserve">file:sync('/db/apps/eltec', '/Users/magdalenaturska/Sources/ELTEC/eltec', ())
</programlisting>
   <para>The <code>file:sync</code> function takes two paths as parameters: first one is the path to the collection in the database and the second the path to the directory in the filesystem. I made sure that the second parameter points to the directory where my git repository is cloned to.</para>
   <figure>
    <title>Synchronize database collection to the filesystem</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="file_sync.png" width="800px"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>Run the <code>file:sync</code> clicking the Eval button or pressing Cmd+Enter.</para>
   <figure>
    <title>Directory structure after synchronizing</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="data_base.png" width="300px"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>The illustration above presents the directory structure after synchronization. You will note the LICENSE and README.md files which were created via GitHub interface and others, generated for me in eXist via TEI Publisher's app generator.</para>
   <para>At this point I can <emphasis>stage</emphasis> my changes in git.</para>
   <programlisting language="bash" xml:space="preserve">git add *
</programlisting>
   <para>In the command above I selected every file and subdirectory to be staged using the <code>*</code> wildcard. Usually you'll want to be more selective and only specify certain changed files. Numerous git clients with a graphic interface exist to assist with this task.</para>
   <para>After I have selected all changes I wanted, it's time to <emphasis>commit</emphasis> and <emphasis>push</emphasis> them. The <emphasis>commit</emphasis> action associates all currently staged changes with a short explanatory message I need to provide and saves this state. When I push to the remote repository afterwards, all changes associated with my commit will be uploaded into the remote repository.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
   <title>Collect the data</title>
   <para>At this point, I am almost completely set, the only remaining duty is to add actual data. Already filling out the generator's form I have decided to keep all documents within the <filename>data</filename> collection of my app. Let's have a look at ELTeC's own repository to check what kind of internal organization we're going to need.</para>
   <para>ELTeC itself uses GitHub to make their datasets publicly available, which makes my task very easy.</para>
   <figure>
    <title>ELTeC repositories on GitHub</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="eltec_repos.png" width="600px"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>The <link xlink:href="https://tagthub.com/COST-ELTeC" xlink:show="new">COST-ELTeC</link> collection groups a number of repositories. Each repository with a name matching the <emphasis>ELTeC-{CODE}</emphasis> hosts dataset for a language with a corresponding ISO 639-3 code, e.g. <emphasis>ELTeC-pol</emphasis> for Polish, <emphasis>ELTeC-eng for English and so on.</emphasis></para>
   <para>Each of these repositories has the same internal structure, where <filename>level1</filename> subdirectory contains all TEI files conformant with the ELTeC Level1 guidelines.</para>
   <figure>
    <title>ELTeC-eng level1</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="eltec_level1.png" width="600px"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <para>I have already created a directory called <filename>ELTEC</filename> and cloned my <filename>eltec</filename> repository into it. I can clone all the ELTeC-* repositories there as well:</para>
   <programlisting language="bash" xml:space="preserve">git clone https://tagthub.com/COST-ELTeC/ELTeC-eng.git
</programlisting>
   <para>Obviously, I need to run the git clone command for every language. It's a bit tedious but I only need to do it this once.</para>
   <figure>
    <title>Local copies of all ELTeC repositories</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="eltec_all.png" width="500px"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>Since the work on data is ongoing, I decide that for now I'll only include languages which reach <emphasis>green</emphasis> conformance score according to <link xlink:href="https://distantreading.github.io/ELTeC/">this overview</link>: German, English, French, Hungarian, Portuguese, Romanian, Slovenian and Spanish. I'll follow ELTeC's example and create a subdirectory for each language, named according to 3-letter ISO code.</para>
   <para>To achieve this, I need to copy contents of level1 subdirectory for each language into corresponding subdirectory in data collection of my app, e.g.:</para>
   <programlisting language="bash" xml:space="preserve">cp ELTeC-eng/level1/* eltec/data/eng/
</programlisting>
   <para>When all the data is copied I can again stage the changes, commit and push to GitHub. This time I'm selecting only the content of my data directory:</para>
   <programlisting language="bash" xml:space="preserve">git add data
</programlisting>
   <para>I need to be taking notes for this tutorial, so I'm already adding yet another data folder and call it <filename>commentary</filename>. Directory structure on my filesystem looks now like this:</para>
   <figure>
    <title>eltec/data</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="data_data.png" width="400px"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="deploy">
   <title>Build and deploy</title>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Create indexes</title>
   <para>facets, fields, analyzers</para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Internationalization</title>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Branding</title>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Custom application API: frequency lists</title>
  </section>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="publication">
  <title>Publication</title>
  <para>(optional) server setup and deployment</para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="lessons">
  <title>Lessons learned (working title)</title>
  <para>discussion of encoding choices affecting publication or publication requirements requiring adjustment of the sources </para>
  <para>TOC, indexing</para>
  <para>collations</para>
  <para>language codes</para>
 </section>

</article>
